I've literally been talking all day, so sorry if my voice is a bit if I'm
coughing.
Okay, so it's a mental health check-in that I hope you'll be doing a lot more
over the
winter because we're doing it every month but it's slipped a bit over the
summer and I think
our calls in general have been quieter over the summer and hopefully now
everyone's getting
back into the swing of things and this is a call that is sometimes much needed
and it's
really nice to do so yeah this is our mental health check-in today and the
theme of it
is living from the inside out which is something I've probably mentioned a
couple of times
before but I'll explain it in more details we go along. There's only sort of
three or
four slides so it's not too much and then I will stop the recording and we'll
share
and do the rest of the call just without the recording on. So you all know who
I am so
I just thought I didn't know whether they were going to be any newbies on the
call but you
know who I am and aside from the ethical calm I'm also a registered psychother
apist so that
is a different part of my life but something that I like to bring into the
group when I
can because it's just so nice to use those skills and to sort of concentrate on
our well-being
and our mental health because it's so important in this and with what we do it
wasn't it and
in general. So yeah how will the call be structured I'll just go through these
slides and then
we'll have some time that's confidential that where we'll just share together.
If you've
got any questions or anything that you want to say that you don't want to say
out loud
just put it in the chat or feel free to message me after if there's anything
that you felt
you wanted to say but you weren't quite brave enough to say it in the group
that's fine as
well I'm happy to chat to anyone after. And just to reiterate what I always say
on these
calls so in order to facilitate a safe face to learn and to share can we all
just be mindful
that anything anybody shares on this call is completely confidential so if
someone shares
you know not saying we're going to go into my life stories although that's okay
if we do but
anything even if you think it's small it might be big to that other person so
let's just anything
we share here let's just keep it on this call after I've stopped the recording
then we know
that confidentiality is in place and of course it goes about same but I'll say
anyway let's just
have empathy and respect for each other because we might have different views
on some things and
also respect each other's autonomy so we might share something and actually we
don't want feedback
on it or we're not looking for advice we're just looking to talk and share so
be aware of what
you want from other people and what they might want from you before you
immediately share with
someone or you know comment on something okay so I'm going to talk a little bit
about living from
the inside out because I think it's really important and it's a way to just
gently start to prioritise
your mental health if you don't really know anything about mental health it's
an easy way to start
so living from the inside out versus outside in so living from the inside out
means engaging our
feelings senses and emotions as a way to navigate through life it means
understanding and trusting
our bodies messages so the feelings emotions and pain that come from our body
if you step on
something sharp you feel physical pain you understand the message that your
body's giving you don't
do that again or change the situation or whatever and you step away you do
something different so
emotional pain should work in the same way we feel something we don't like it
you know we get a message
that something's not safe so we avoid it or we change it or we take the
necessary steps and overcome
that pain living from the inside out means trusting your inner guidance not
living according to other
people's ideas or expectations but to our own feelings and needs just as nature
intended
so it's quite simple but quite hard as well so I'll talk a little bit more
about it so you can
get more of an idea of what it means so why don't we do it and why don't many
of us do this we don't
live this way so humans are the only species on earth who because of our
dependency on our caregivers
when we're born because we're so helpless as babies we've forgotten often how
to use our
internal navigation system so how to be guided by our inner feelings and
emotions to survive it's a
baby we need to be heard we need to communicate with our needs so we need to
cry and we need to
have the mess so we need to have a caregiver that listens to our cry and comes
to feed us or whatever
else we need so we need to be valued by that person for our survival our life
literally depends on how
worthy another person thinks we are once we reach an age when we're able to
look after our own needs
we should then be able to do so by listening to our body so instead of crying
out for help we
should be able to think I'm hungry you know and then and then go for food but
sometimes due to
insufficient caregiving by no fault of the caregiver sometimes or unhealthy
societal norms you know
you're telling a child telling a child off or whatever it is we often learn to
distrust our inner
feelings so we learn that what we're feeling on the inside either doesn't
matter or is not correct
and we keep living from the outside in so we no longer trust what's happening
inside our own body
we revert to listening to what other people say what what we hear what society
says or whatever
else is happening in the outside environment is ruling how we feel inside oops
so
yeah living life the opposite way from the outside in means living life through
your mind
and not through your body it means always trying to do the right thing by other
people
and neglecting your own needs it means people pleasing self-shaming self-doubt
low confidence limiting beliefs and loads of other things the good news is we
can change it
so I did a little diagram just to try and make it more clear what I'm talking
about when I talk
about from the inside out versus living from the outside in so on the left hand
side when we live
from the inside out our values intentions and emotions shape our relationship
circumstances
and life so it starts inside of us it's like prime manifestation state and then
it affects our
outer world when we're living from the outside in like on the right hand side
our relationship
circumstances and life shape our values and emotions so the stuff that's
happening outside
the horrible stuff you see on the news all the time arguments in the family who
you think you
should be what other people judge you all that just comes in and affects how
you feel so you're
not having the feelings first and then the stuff you're having the stuff first
and then the feelings
um I won't go too much into detail on these but I just thought I'd put this on
just because
it's not an easy thing to do to begin to live from the inside out it's not an
easy thing to do and
that's because there are many different blocks to it there are many different
things that prevent
us from doing it and these are some of the things and it's just some of them
but over dependence on
others so sometimes we're dependent on other people financially you know so we
we have to
listen to what they say and we have to care more about their judgment than ours
or that's just one
example sometimes we have unprocessed trauma so we're not quite sure how to
listen to what's going
on inside because there's so much in there that we haven't cleared it out we
can't read the messages
clearly there's too much there so we need to talk to someone and process it
work through it
um identity fears so sometimes what stops us from prioritising our own feelings
and using our
inner guidance is that we feel our identity is so much about giving other
people what they want
and we only feel like we're okay when we are you know serving other people so
you can get
so mixed up with your identity and that's one thing that stops us from doing it
society of course
you know it's quite toxic it stops us you know particularly as women it tells
us what we should
shouldn't do and you know depending on how privileged we are or we're not with
our circumstances
suffers from doing it as well avoidance of emotions so if we just think we have
to like a lot of
99% of my clients say when they start because it's just like normal language in
our culture
controlled our emotions so if we think we have to control our emotions you know
that's really
unhealthy it's actually avoidance of emotions it's just suppressing them and
shutting them off
so you can't get those messages either and and relationship systems so that's
one big big thing
that stops many many people from listening to their inner guidance is that when
you're in a family
so a family is a relationship system and the whole system is dependent on you
being the one who
I don't know the picture we want to take here on a Monday does this on a
Tuesday you know has a
certain role in the family where you're taking on loads of responsibility or
maybe you're the
one in the family that you're the only one that everyone opens up to
emotionally there's loads of
different things so relational systems sometimes is the one thing that stops us
from doing this as
well because if we stop doing that it's going to affect everybody else so we
have to abandon
ourselves in order to keep everyone else happy so the last one don't want to go
on too much and
I'm starting to lose my voice so how do we start doing it how do we start
listening to our inner
guidance which is so important which is at the root of all our well-being
mental health physically
and emotionally how do we start listening to it what little things can we do to
start this process
the first thing work on any unprocessed emotions or trauma so if there's
anything there that's
just that with you you know then we need to clear that stuff up first otherwise
it makes it really
different difficult to listen to what's going on inside and so with a therapist
with a registered
therapist you can work through that stuff you can release it and let it go let
go of shame and
any other hold that it has on you and you can listen you can start to do this
you know as a
practice every day listen to your body's cues and think about the need behind
what it's saying
so your body is giving you a cue it's talking to you it's communicating with
you when you feel
like that pang of like guilt or regret or anger or whatever it is there's a
need there that's not
being met so when you feel something rather than shaming yourself out of it and
they can go straight
into your mind and thinking shouldn't be thinking the risks of that madness you
know you're explaining
it away or repressing it or just avoiding it or just doing something else just
sit with it just sit
with the feeling for a minute and just just think about what need is not being
met here you know take
away shame from it because we our emotions are there for a reason and think how
could I be navigated
by that by that thing that's coming up what is it trying to teach me and allow
time to stillness
so one big way of avoiding your inner navigation or your inner you know this
really strong thing
you've got this inner compass is by being busy all the time or having constant
distractions so
being struck by your relationship and then it's friend drama and then it's
something else something
else or with something in the house or whatever we're in this either constant
rush or constant
distraction and it stops us from listening to anything there sometimes because
we're fearful
of what's in there but stillness needs to happen in order for us to start
sitting with what we feel
and connect to ourselves a bit better and try to remove shame from your
behaviours so the reason
why we do anything ever is because we're trying to either protect ourselves or
it's a habit that
we've built up over time because we've reacted to something and this habit has
worked it's become
habitual so none of your behaviours you know are mean that you're a bad person
if you're doing a
certain thing it doesn't even mean that you're a weak person you're always
giving in to the one
that doesn't mean you're weak it just means that you are one protecting
yourself or two at some point
you felt you had to protect yourself and now it's just a habit so try to remove
shame from your
behaviours and it will help you to get closer to yourself and listen to what
your body's trying
to tell you and lastly remember you are worthy I know this is so cheesy but it
's so true and so
important remember you're worthy and you've only ever done your best all any of
us are doing is our
best you know it works with many many different people from many walks of life
you know criminals
or all sorts and we're only ever all doing our best you know we all just want
to be loved and
accepted we all just want to be safe and we're all just doing our best with the
information that
we've got so trying to remove that shame and come back to that and whenever you
're not dealing it
okay so that's it from for me um my incessant chatter
I'm gonna turn the recording off now so um
oh I was thinking shall I share something before I turned it off no I won't I
'll turn it off first
so I'm gonna turn it off and then please don't feel any pressure but for anyone
that wants to
have a check in you know if you want a structure you can just tell is something
that's going well
for you at the moment and something that you're struggling with or if you don't
need structure
you can just share you can just share to ask a question or you can share to
just just be heard
and just so that we can listen to each other I'm going to stop the recording
let's stop the share first